Okay, good morning class.
好的，早上课。
So we are today doing the rise
今天我们来讲罗马帝国的兴起。
and fall of the Roman Empire.
以及它的衰落。
And this topic is extremely relevant today
本题今天非常贴切
because there's a country in the world that
因为世界上有一个国家
purposefully modeled itself out of Rome.
它有意地以罗马为模型
And this country is the United States of America.
并且这国家就是美利合众国。
The similarities between Rome
罗马与美利合众国之间的相似之处，十分显著。
and the United States, it's very striking.
Both of these societies were of
这两大社会都是各自时代最强大的民族国家。
their time the most powerful nations.
罗马统治西方数百年。
Rome dominated the Western world for centuries.
And today America is the world's most powerful nation.
而今美国已是世界最强大的民族国家。
In fact,
事实上，
America is so powerful that
美国的实力如此强大，
if the entire world were to get together and
如果全世界聚在一起并
decide for whatever reason to invade and attack America
决定出于任何原因入侵并攻击美国
and not stop until America was defeated,
并且不停止直到美国被击败
well if that were to happen, America would win.
如果那样发生，阿美会赢。
America is really invincible.
美国真是无敌的。
It's protected by two oceans and it has infinite resources.
它被两海环抱，资源无穷。
And it has an extremely aggressive
并且它拥有极其积极的…
and it has an extremely aggressive population and the world's most sophisticated military.
并且它拥有极其积极的人口与世界最精密的军队。
So by sitting in Rome,
于是坐落在罗马之中。
we gather insight into America,
我们收集关于美国的洞见，
where America is right now in its history and where America is headed.
在美国历史的现在位置以及未来方向。
And a central argument I will make to you today is
今天我要给你们提出的核心论点是。
that both of these societies,
那两种社会，
Rome and America,
罗马与美国，
are really are really war machines.
都是真正的战争机器。
They're extremely aggressive. And
他们极其积极。且
if they cannot turn their aggression outwards, they turn their aggression inwards.
若他们不能把这种积极向外转移，就会向内转移。
Rome throughout its history was either fighting wars against its enemies,
罗马在其历史中，始终是与其敌人作战。
and then when it ran out of enemies,
然后当它没有敌人时，
it fought wars within itself,
它在内部打起战争，
which ultimately led to its decline and collapse.
最终导致其衰落与崩溃。
America is in a very similar situation.
美国正处于类似的局面。
After the fall of the Soviet Union, in 1912, the Soviet Union was in a very difficult situation.
苏联解体后，1912年，苏联陷入极其艰难的境地。
In 1921, America became a hyper -power.
1921年，美国成为超级大国。
It had no competitors.
它没有竞争者。
It has no peers in the world.
它在世界上没有同等国。
Even though it tries very hard to look for enemies,
即使它努力寻找敌人，
for example, for the past ten years,
例如，过去十年里，
America has been trying to pay China as a new threat.
美国一直把中国视为新威胁。
America really has no adversaries.
美国确实没有对手。
And as a result,
于是，
it can't really be aggressive abroad.
它在国外并不具备真正的进攻性。
And as a result, it can't really be aggressive abroad. So this will lead to a very difficult situation.
于是，它在国外并不具备真正的进攻性。于是就会导致一个非常困难的局面。
If the history of Rome is an indicator,
如果说罗马的历史是一个指示，
it will probably lead to a massive civil
它很可能会导致一次大规模的内战。
war in America in the next ten years.
十年后美洲的战争。
So that's what the history of Rome tells us.
这就是罗马历史告诉我们的。
Today, I want to look at three questions.
今天，我想探讨三个问题。
The first question is,
第一个问题是，
why did Rome rise?
罗马为何崛起？
What allowed Rome to become an empire, a superpower of its time?
是什么让罗马成为当时的帝国、超级大国？
The second question is,
第二个问题是，
why did Rome ultimately decline and fall?
罗马最终衰落的原因是什么？
The third question is, what is the legacy of Rome?
第三个问题是，罗马的遗产是什么？
What is the impact and influence of Rome in today's world?
罗马在今天世界的影响和作用是什么？
Let's look at the first question.
先看第一个问题。
So Rome, the tradition,
于是罗马，传统，
we don't actually know if this is true or not, but the tradition is
我们不确定这是否属实，但传统认为
that Rome was founded in 753 BCE.
罗马建于公元前753年。
And for that early history, Rome was a monarchy.
而在那早期，罗马是君主制。
It had a king. Then in 509 BCE,
它有一位国王。随后在公元前509年，它成为了一个共和国。
it became a republic.
不是民主，而是共和国。
Not a democracy, a republic.
Not a democracy,a republic.
And then, and
然后，且
at that point, Rome was very much a poor,
在那时，罗马非常贫穷，
backward, and
落后，且
isolated city along the Tiber.
位于提伯河畔的孤立城镇。
And at that point, Rome was a very much a poor, backward, and isolated city along the Tiber.
此时的罗马是一座极其贫穷、落后、孤立的提伯河畔城镇。
And at that point, Rome was a very much a poor, backward, and isolated city along the Tiber. In its history, no one, not even the Romans,
could have predicted that in 300 years' time,
可预见300年后，罗马将成为其世界的主宰，
Rome would become the master of its world,
罗马将成为其世界的主宰，地中海的主宰。
the Mediterranean. In its history, no one, not even the Romans, could have predicted that in 300 years' time, Rome would become the master of its world, the Mediterranean.
To understand why Rome was able to succeed,
为了解罗马为何能成功，
let me very quickly draw for you a map of the world,
请让我快速为你绘制一张世界地图，
the Mediterranean. In about 500 BCE,
大约公元前五百年的地中海。
when the Roman Republic was founded.
当罗马共和国成立时。
So, at the center of this world was really the Persian Empire.
于是，这个世界的中心确实是波斯帝国。
The Persian Empire was in control
波斯帝国掌控着一切。
of the world's three most prosperous regions.
世界三大繁荣地区的其中之一。
Egypt, Anatolia, which
埃及、安纳托利亚，即现代土耳其，和美索不达米亚，即现代伊拉克。
is modern -day Turkey, and Mesopotamia, which is modern -day Iraq.
And these are the three most fertile regions of the Western world.
以及这三处是西方最肥沃的地区。
It was extremely prosperous,
极为繁荣，
very heavily populated.
人口极为稠密。
And the Persian Empire was in control of the three most prosperous regions of the Western world.
波斯帝国掌控西方三大繁荣地区。
So, the Persian Empire is like this.
于是，波斯帝国就是这样。
Across the Aegean and
跨爱琴海与
the Mediterranean from the Persian Empire are the Greeks.
地中海从波斯帝国到希腊人。
You had Athens and you had Sparta.
你有雅典也有斯巴。
And these were the two dominant city -states,
于是这就是两大城邦，
or what were called polis, on the Greek mainland.
或者说是希腊本土的两大城邦，
Across the Adriatic is, of course, Italy.
从亚得里亚海来看，当然是意大利。
And the dominant power actually in Italy at this time are not the Romans.
在此时的意大利真正的霸权并非罗马人。
But a culture civilization we call the Etruscans.
而是我们称之为伊特鲁斯坎的文化文明。
And the Etruscans, for the longest time,
伊特鲁斯坎在很长一段时间里是如此。
were dominant over the Romans.
在此时的意大利真正的霸权并非罗马人。
In fact, some people believe that
实际上，有人认为……
Rome was originally a colony of the Etruscans.
罗马最初是伊特鲁斯坎的殖民。
And the first kings of Rome were actually Etruscans.
并且罗马的第一批国王实际上是伊特鲁斯坎人。
So they were actually Etruscans, princes. And
于是他们实际上是伊特鲁斯坎人，王子。并且……
then over here is a place called Carthage,
随后此处有一处名为迦特加的地方。
which is an emerging power.
它是一支崛起的势力。
And
而且
over here above the Greeks are the Macedonians.
在此处，希腓人之上为马其人。
So these are the major cultures
于是这些就是当时的主要文化与势力。
and powers of that time.
现在，其中一股势力最终将占据主导地位。
Now, one of these powers will eventually dominate
Now, one of these powerswill eventually dominate
and then
然后
provide the cultural framework for all of Western civilization.
为西方文明提供文化框架。
And if we were to go back in time and we were to analyze this situation,
若我们回溯时间并分析此情形，
then we could make some predictions.
然后我们可以做一些预测。
Our first prediction would be that
我们的第一个预测是
Persia would eventually conquer all of Europe.
波斯将最终征服整个欧洲。
Because Persia had infinite wealth,
因为波斯拥有无尽的财富，
it had infinite resources,
它拥有无尽的资源。
it was a superpower that
它是一支超级大国，
was intent on aggression.
意图发动侵略。
And in fact, as we know,
而且，正如我们所知，
eventually it will launch an invasion of the Greek mainland.
最终它将发动对希腊本土的入侵。
So if we were to predict or guess
于是我们若要预测或猜测
who would dominate the world,
谁将主宰世界
we would think it would be Persia.
我们会认为它会是波斯。
That's our first guess. But let's just say,
这就是我们的第一个猜测。
then who would be second?
然后谁会是第二？
Well, we would think that
嗯，我们会认为……
either Athens or Sparta would be second.
亚得斯或斯巴达会是第二位。
Why? Because Athens has a navy.
因为亚得斯有海军。
And it is a really powerful navy.
它是一支非常强大的海军。
And at this time, Greek civilization is really growing.
此时希腊文明正蓬勃发展。
So we would guess Athens or Sparta.
于是我们会猜测是雅典或斯巴达。
And remember, Athens has a navy.
记得，雅典拥有海军。
But Sparta is really a military hegemon.
但斯巴达真是个军事霸权。
It is focused on being a military powerhouse.
它专注于成为军事强国。
And it has really the best military increase at this time.
此时它的军事提升最为显著。
So our third guess might be Sparta.
于是我们的第三个猜测可能是斯巴达。
Then we could guess Carthage. Why?
然后我们可以猜测迦特拉。为什么？
Because Carthage is strategically located in Northern Africa,
因为迦特拉位于北非的战略位置。
which gives it access to all trade routes in Africa,
它让它能接触非洲所有贸易路线，
over here, into all of Europe,
在此处，通往欧洲所有地区，
and then back to the Mediterranean.
随后再回到地中海。
So Carthage would also be a good guess.
于是迦特拉也是一个不错的猜测。
We would not guess Macedonia.
我们不猜马其顿。
Why? Because Macedonia is a poor,
为什么？因为马其顿是个贫穷的…
backward kingdom north of Greece
希腊北方的后王国
that's being controlled right now by the Persians.
正被波斯人统治的那片土地
We would never guess Macedonia.
我们从不猜马其顿
And then there's one city
然后还有一个城市
that we would never, ever believe
我们永远都不会相信
could dominate the world, and that's Rome.
它能主宰世界，那就是罗马。
Rome would not be on our list.
罗马不在我们的列表里。
Macedonia might be on the list because it still has a strategic location,
马其顿可能在列表里，因为它仍有战略位置，
it has a very militant population,
它有非常多的军人。
but we would never, ever guess Rome.
但我们永远都不会猜到罗马。
Now what's funny about these predictions, of course, is that
现在这些预测有趣的地方当然是……
eventually Rome does conquer
最终罗马确实征服了
the entire Mediterranean world, and
整个地中海世界，且
it becomes the superpower of its time,
它成为当时的超级大国，
and then it develops the cultural framework for all of Western civilization.
随后它为西方文明奠定了文化框架
But not only that,
但不只是这样，
but close to Rome is Macedonia.
而且罗马附近是马其顿。
Because remember, Macedonia is where
因为记得，马其顿是……
Philip II builds the world's most powerful military, and
菲利普二世打造了世界最强大的军队，且
where Alexander the Great comes from to conquer all the Persian Empire.
亚历山大大帝从此出发，征服波斯帝国
So it's very strange that the nations
于是国度很奇怪
that either are not on the list or are on the bottom list will eventually conquer the world.
那些不在列表上或在底部列表上的国家最终会征服世界。
And this goes back to our first class,
而这回到我们第一节课，
where we talked about the oceanic currents of history,
我们在那节课里谈到历史的海洋流动
how empires are destined to fall, to decline,
帝国衰落、衰退的规律
but in the process, they energize these borderlands,
但在过程中，它们激活了这些边疆
and empower these borderlands to rise,
并赋予这些边疆以崛起
and eventually, over time, to overwhelm the empire.
并最终，随着时间，压倒帝国。
So this is true for Macedonia, and this is certainly true for Rome.
于是这对马其里亚来说是如此，对罗马也如此。
So this fits into our pattern of the oceanic currents of history. So
于是这与历史的海洋流动模式相符。
there are many different reasons why Rome would eventually
有许多种原因导致罗马最终…
win out over its competitors in the Mediterranean.
在地中海赢得竞争对手
What I want to focus on today are the cultural reasons.
我今天想聚焦的，是文化原因。
So my argument today is that Rome,
所以，我今天的论点是罗马，
in opposition to its enemies,
在与其敌人对抗时，
developed a cultural system that
发展了一套文化体系
allowed it to triumph over its enemies.
使其能战胜敌人。
This cultural system made it ideal for military competition
这一文化体系使其成为军事竞争的理想之选。
against its major enemies.
对其主要敌人。
Okay? So,
好的？
let's talk about this cultural system.
让我们来谈谈这个文化体系。
And to understand this cultural system,
为了理解这个文化体系，
I will compare and contrast it with the Greeks, who are also, who
我将把它与希腊人进行比较与对照，后者也是，基本上是此时此地最具文化主导力的民族。
are basically the most culturally dominant people in this area at this time.
Okay. So what do the Greeks believe in?
好的。那么希腊人信奉什么？
Well, the Greeks believe in three things.
嗯，希腊人信奉三件事。
Okay? The Greek system.
好的？希腊人的体系。
When I mean Greeks, I basically mean the Athenians.
当我说希腊人时，我基本上指的是雅典人。
Okay? Because the Athenians were the culturally dominant
好？因为雅典人是希腊世界里文化主导的民族。
nation in the Greek world.
All right. So what do the Greeks believe in, and how were the Romans different?
好的。那么希腊人信奉什么？
Well, first thing to understand is that
嗯，首先要理解的是……
Greeks were culturally dominant.
希腊人是文化上的主导者。
And so what happened was that
于是发生的事是……
Romans developed a lot of their cultural system in opposition,
罗马人把自己的文化体系大多在对抗希腊的基础上发展起来，
to the Greeks.
……
Or they learned lessons from the Greeks.
或者他们从希腊人那里学到经验。
Okay? So think about as analogy,
好的？所以请把它当作比喻，
the relationship between China and Japan.
中日两国的关系。
A lot of Japanese cultural systems and
大量的日本文化体系和
values were developed in opposition to China
价值观在对抗中国的过程中形成
and because of the lessons that
并因从中国的经验中汲取
the Japanese learned from Chinese history.
日语从中国历史中学到的内容。
Okay? So, what,
好的？那么，什么，
let's talk about the Greeks. What Greek values,
让我们谈谈希腊人。希腊人的价值观，
and then what values the Romans developed in opposition to the Greeks.
然后罗马人对希腊人形成的价值观是什么？
Okay? So the first value the Greeks developed was the idea of freedom.
好吧？希腊人首先形成的价值观是自由的概念。
What is freedom? Freedom represents an egalitarian society in
自由是什么？自由代表一种平等的社会。
which everyone has the right to speak his mind.
每个人都有权利说出自己的想法。
His, not hers. Okay? His mind.
他的，而不是她的。好的？他的想法。
So every citizen was considered equal.
于是每个公民都被视为平等。
And that was the basis for Greek democracy.
于是这成为希腊民主的基础。
Everyone who has the right, everyone has the right to speak.
凡有权利的人，皆有发言之权。
If you're a citizen. Okay?
若你是公民。好的？
Now what is the Roman counterpart?
现在罗马的对应词是什么？
The Roman counterpart is what we call liberty.
罗马的对应词就是我们所说的自由。
And they sound similar, but they're actually very different concepts.
它们听起来相似，实际上却是两种完全不同的概念。
Freedom is the right to speak your mind.
自由是发言之权。
The right to live your life.
是活出自己生活的权利。
Liberty is the respect of the people.
自由即人民的敬意。
For the laws, history,
法律、历史、你的文化传统。
and traditions of your culture.
因为这让你们能自由。
Because that's what enables you to be free.
If we don't respect the laws, it would be anarchy.
若不遵守法律，便是混乱。
Also, liberty means basically no king. Okay?
自由基本上就是没有国王。好吗？
We will never allow a king to rule us.
我们永不让国王统治我们。
Because he takes away our liberty.
因为他夺走了我们的自由。
What's interesting for us is,
对我们来说有趣的，是……
the modern Western concept is
现代西方概念是
more aligned with the Romans than the Greeks.
更贴近罗马而非希腊。
When we think of freedom and liberty,
当我们想到自由与自由时，
we think of the Roman idea, not the Greek idea.
我们想到的是罗马观念，而非希腊观念。
So liberty. The Roman word for this is, of course, libertas.
于是自由。罗马语里这个词当然是libertas。
Alright. The second idea,
好了。第二个概念，
value of the Greeks, is the idea of eudaimonia.
希腊的价值观是eudaimonia的概念。
Eudaimonia is the pursuit of human flourishing.
eudaimonia是人类繁荣的追求。
To be the best that you can be.
成为你能成为的最好。
To be better than your peers, and to win respect for your peers.
优于同辈，赢得同辈的敬重。
To seek glory.
去追求荣耀。
To seek honor. So let's go back to last semester,
去追求荣誉。于是我们回到上学期，
and think about Achilles in the epic,
思考阿基琉斯在史诗中的形象。
the Iliad. Achilles was in Troy,
《伊利亚特》里，阿基琉斯在特洛伊城中，
not to Westeros, not to win glory for the Greek people,
不是为了维斯特洛斯，也不是为了给希腊人赢得荣耀，
but to win glory for himself.
而是为了给自己赢得荣耀。
He was extremely selfish, he was extremely competitive.
他非常自私，竞争心极强。
And he was so competitive,
他竞争心极强，
that when he abandoned the battlefield,
当他离开战场时
he basically asked his mother, Thetis, the goddess, to get Zeus,
他基本上向母亲提提斯——女神——求助，求宙斯——高神——偏袒特洛伊人。
the high god, to favor the Trojans.
这就是叛国。又是起义。
This is treason. This is sedition.
This is treason.This is sedition.
And for the Greeks, this is good, because what's important is, to win eudaimonia.
对希腊人来说，这很好，因为重要的是赢得eudaimonia。
You, in order to achieve eudaimonia, can do anything, because that's what matters.
你要想获得eudaimonia，可以做任何事，因为这才是关键。
Okay? And
好吧？
the idea of eudaimonia, if you think about it, it's what led to Greek creativity.
若想一想，eudaimonia的概念就是促成希腊创造力的根源。
Because everyone saw society as a competition,
因为大家把社会视作一场竞赛，
and they want to be the best.
于是他们都想成为最优者。
Okay? But if you think about it, it also leads to corruption,
好吧？但想想看，它也会导致腐败与自私。好吧？
and selfishness. Okay?
于是罗马人不喜欢eudaimonia。
So the Romans didn't like eudaimonia.
Instead, their highest virtue was the idea of repubblica.
相反，罗马人的最高美德是“repubblica”概念。
And this is where we get the word republic from.
这就是“共和国”一词的来源。
Republica means for the greater good, for the public virtue.
repubblica意为为大义、为公共美德。
So what's important is not that you win glory for yourself,
于是重要的不是你为自己赢得荣耀，
but to sacrifice yourself for the greater good,
而是为更大的利益而自我牺，
for the good of Rome.
为罗马的福祉。
That's what made you a good person.
这就是让你成为好人的原因。
Or the best person. To fight and die for Rome.
或者说是最好的那个人。为罗马而战、而死。
And the third value for the Greeks
以及希腊人第三个价值。
that mattered was the idea of erite.
那件事重要的是埃里特的概念。
Erete just means excellence.
埃里特只是指卓越。
So even though Achilles was a jerk, the Greeks still admired him.
所以即使阿基琉斯是个傻瓜，希腊人仍然敬佩他。
Why? Because he was a great soldier.
为什么？因为他是位伟大的战士。
On the battlefield, he was fabulous.
在战场上，他表现出色。
He was excellent. And therefore, he should be admired.
他很出色，因此值得敬佩。
Okay? The Romans didn't like this.
好的？罗马人不喜欢这样。
Okay? They didn't want people to outshine everyone else.
好的？他们不想让别人比他们更出色。
So they prefer the concept of piety.
于是他们更喜欢“敬礼”这一概念。
Obedience, loyalty to your fathers,
服从，忠于父亲，
to Rome, to the gods.
服从，忠于罗马，忠于诸神。
Piety is what mattered.
敬礼才是关键。
The highest virtue in Rome
罗马最高的美德
is not erite. It is piety.
不是“礼”而是“敬礼”。
And again,
再一次，
a lot of Roman values was developed in response to the Greeks.
大量罗马价值观是在对希腊的回应中形成的。
Especially to the Athenians.
尤其是对雅典人的回应。
Okay? Because remember, the Athenians in 480,
好吧？因为记得，雅典人在公元前480年……
they defeated the Persians.
他们击败了波斯人。
And the Athenians became basically an empire.
雅典人基本上成为了一个帝国。
They were the dominant military force in the Mediterranean
他们是地中海的主导军力。
and the Aegean all of that time.
以及爱琴海的那段时间。
But 80 years later, 400,
但80年后，400年，
they had been decimated. They had been destroyed.
他们已被夷灭。
They fought against Sparta in the Peloponnesian War, and they lost.
他们在伯罗奔尼战争中与斯巴达作战，最终败北。
The Romans witnessed all this.
罗马人见证了这一切。
Right? Because they were just across from the Adriatic.
对吧？因为他们就在亚得里亚海对岸。
They knew all this. And so
他们都知道这一切。于是他们决定不再重蹈罗马的覆辙。
they were determined not to repeat the mistakes of Rome.
他们决意不再重蹈雅典的覆辙。
They were determined to not to repeat the mistakes of the Athenians. And
that's why they developed a system in opposition to the Greeks,
这就是他们在对抗希腊时所建的制度的缘起，
the Athenians. The Athenians had democracy.
雅典人有民主制。
And it was common wisdom at that time that
当时人们普遍认为
it was the democratic system that
它是民主制度导致了雅典帝国的崩溃。
caused the collapse of the Athenian Empire.
于是罗马人建立了共和国这一制度。
And in response, the Romans developed a system called the Republic.
随后罗马人发展出了共和国这一制度。
Now, there's a huge difference
现在，阿美式民主与共和国之间有很大差别。它们听起来一样。
between American democracy and republic. They sound the same.
而在今天的世界里，我们把这两个概念交替使用。
And in today's world, we use these two concepts interchangeably.
We say American democracy.
我们说美国民主。
We say American republic. It means the same thing.
我们说美国共和国。它们是同一个意思。
But back then, democracy and
但在那时，民主和
republic were two opposing systems.
共和国是两种相对的制度。
So let me give you an example to show you how different this system is.
让我举个例子来说明这个制度有多不同。
So democracy is basically one man, one vote.
民主基本上是“一人一票”。
It encourages competition, encourages debate, encourages free thought.
它促进竞争，促进辩论，促进自由思考。
Republic is to be ruled by institutions,
共和国是由制度治理，
basically the Senate, okay?
基本是参议院，好吗？
Institutions. By laws.
机构。以法律为准。
And by history or tradition.
以历史或传统为准。
All right, so what's the difference?
好了，差别在哪？
All right. Let's pretend that we're all going to go out for lunch today.
好的。我们假装今天一起去吃午饭。
And each of us has a different opinion.
我们每个人都有不同的想法。
I want to go to McDonald's
我想去麦当劳。
Eva wants to go and get dumplings.
艾娃想去买饺子。
Echo wants to go to pizza.
埃科想去吃比萨。
Who knows, okay? But we all have these different opinions.
谁知道呢，好吗？但我们都有这些不同的想法。
In a democracy, we resolve this issue by having debate.
在民主制度里，我们通过辩论来解决这个问题。
I make my argument for my idea.
我为自己的想法陈述论点。
Then you all make your argument for your ideas, okay?
然后你们各自为自己的想法陈述论点，好吗？
And then we vote. And the majority wins.
然后我们投票，得票多者胜。
Simple, right? Okay.
简单吧？好了。
A republic is different.
共和国则不同。
A republic, you make your decisions based on tradition.
一个共和国，你们的决策基于传统。
So for example, today is Thursday.
比如说，今天是星期四。
And for whatever reason, we don't know why,
不管原因是什么，我们都不去问。
but every Thursday, we go out to get dumplings.
但每个星期四我们就去吃饺子。
So guess what?
于是你猜怎么回事？
We just go and get dumplings. We don't ask why.
我们直接去吃饺子，问不着原因。
We don't even know why. We may not even like dumplings.
我们甚至不知道为什么。也许我们甚至不喜欢饺子。
It doesn't matter. What matters is you respect
这不重要。重要的是你要尊重
and follow tradition set by your fathers.
并遵循你祖先设立的传统。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这样说通吗？
Now,
现在，
what's interesting is these two systems
有趣的是这两套体系都有优点和后果。
have benefits and consequences.
And it's the idea of the republic that
并且正是共和国的理念使得
allows Rome to eventually
罗马最终得以…
conquer the entire Mediterranean.
征服整个地中海。
And the reason why is the idea of a republic solves a problem
而之所以如此，是因为共和国的理念解决了问题。
that democracy cannot solve.
那是民主无法解决的事。
It's the idea of citizenship. And identity.
它是公民身份的概念。
The way you organize your society is basically through citizenship.
你们组织社会的方式基本上是通过公民身份。
Okay? Who gets to be a citizen?
好的？谁能成为公民？
Who doesn't? Now democracy is actually very hard to be a citizen.
谁没？现在民主真的很难成为公民。
Because if we are having a debate and
因为如果我们正在辩论
competition, we don't want others coming into the system.
竞争，我们不想让其他人进入系统。
Right? There's four of us in the classroom.
对吗？我们四个人在教室里。
We debate. But let's just say we let in five other people.
我们讨论。只是说我们又让五个人加入。
And we let in five people. And these five other people all love noodles.
我们又让五个人加入。这五个人都爱吃面条。
Guess what? We're stuck going to noodles every day.
猜怎么回事？我们每天都去吃面条。
Right? So we don't want newcomers.
对吧？所以我们不想有新人。
And that's why the Athenian Empire fell.
而这就是雅典帝国衰落的原因。
The Athenian Empire had to fight these wars to protect its empire.
雅典帝国必须发动这些战争来保卫其帝国。
But in each battle, it had to lose soldiers.
但在每场战斗里，它必须失去士兵。
Even if you win battles, you have to lose soldiers.
即使你赢得战斗，也必失去士兵。
And it could not replenish these soldiers
它无法补充这些士兵
because it did not want foreigners to become citizens.
因为它不想让外来人成为公民。
Does that make sense? But in a republic, you do not have this problem.
那有道理吗？但在一个共和国里，你就不会遇到这个问题。
Right? If we are a republic, and we're all stuck going to noodles
对吗？如果我们是共和国，而且我们都要去吃面条
every Thursday, we let in 100 people.
每个星期四，我们让100人进来。
Doesn't matter. We're all going to noodles. Right?
不管怎样。我们都去吃面条。对吗？
It doesn't affect us. So the beauty of a republic is
它不影响我们。所以共和国的美在于你可以接纳移民
you can allow immigrants and
并且…
foreigners to come into your system,
外来者进入你的体系，
which allows you to replenish your military.
这使你能补充军力。
Right? And they become citizens
对吗？他们就会成为公民
if they are willing to fight for you and if they're willing to follow your traditions,
如果他们愿意为你而战并愿意遵循你的传统
your customs, your history.
你的风俗，你的历史。
And it's very similar in America.
而在美国也很相似。
Right? In China, how are you a citizen?
对吗？在中国，你怎么算是公民？
Well, you're born here, and both your parents are Chinese.
嗯，你在这里出生，父母都是中国人。
And that's it. Okay? There's no other way to become a Chinese citizen.
好了，就是这样。对吗？成为中国公民只有这条路。
But in America, you can immigrate and just say,
在美国，你可以移民，然后说……
I swear to obey the Constitution.
我发誓遵守宪法。
I swear to protect the Constitution.
我发誓护宪法。
If you say those words, you can become a U.S.
若你说出这些话，你就能成为美国人。
citizen. Okay?
公民。对吗？
So that's the power of the republic.
这就是民族国家的力量。
Okay? So let's talk about some historical examples
好了，接下来聊聊一些历史例子。
to illustrate the difference between a democracy and a republic.
用来说明民主与共和国的区别。
Well, in a democracy,
好吧，在民主中，
people understand polis, or society, as a community of people.
人们把城邦或社会视为一群人。
Okay? So the example is, in 480,
好的？所以例子是，480年，
the Persians invaded the Greek mainland, and
波斯人入侵希腊本土，且
they were about to attack Athens.
他们正准备进攻雅典。
And there was no way that Athens could withstand
于是雅典根本无力抵御波斯进攻。
the Persian onslaught.
于是他们做了什么？他们做的事是……
So what did they do? Well, what they did was,
they got onto their ships, and they sailed away.
他们乘船出发。
The entire Athenian people, the entire city of Athens,
整个雅典人，整个雅典城，登船出发。
got onto the ships and sailed away.
他们乘船离开。
And the Persians were like, well,
于是波斯人说，嗯，你们能做到吗？
you can't do that. And the Athenians said, yes, we can.
雅典人回答，当然可以。
Because as a community, we can be wherever we want.
因为作为一个社区，我们可以随时随地成为它
We don't have to be in Athens.
我们不必在雅典。
As long as we're a community, we will be Athens.
只要我们是一个社区，我们就是雅典。
We can leave Athens and go sail to Africa, and
我们可以离开雅典，乘船航行至非洲。
we will still be Athens.
我们仍然是雅典。
Okay? That's the idea of community.
好的？这就是社区的意思。
But the Romans didn't believe that.
但罗马人并不这么认为。
Remember, in 216,
记得，216年，
Hannibal comes and
汉尼拔来袭，攻占意大利半岛。
attacks the Italian peninsula.
He destroys and wipes out all the Roman armies.
他摧毁并消灭了所有罗马军队。
Rome has no army. And at this point,
罗马没有军队。此时，
Rome has options.
罗马有选择。
It can surrender, or it can leave.
它可以投降，也可以离开。
It cannot leave because
它不能离开，因为
to leave Rome would be to abandon its identity
离开罗马就是离开它的身份
as a Roman people.
作为罗马人。
If you're a republic,
如果你是一个共和国，
the place does matter.
地点很重要。
Once you leave the place,
一旦离开地点，
you abandon the values,
你放弃了价值观，
the culture, the history that makes you distinctly Roman.
文化，历史，这些让你们成为独特的罗马人。
So the Romans said to Hannibal, we will not surrender.
于是罗马人对汉尼拔说：我们不投降。
We will fight the last man if you come and attack us.
我们会与最后一人作战，若你来袭击我们。
And Hannibal never did.
汉尼拔从未曾如此。
Okay? And
好的？
what's really funny about this incident is
这件事最有趣的地方是
it's really the proudest moment in Roman history.
这真是罗马历史中最骄傲的时刻。
Okay? They were up against impossible odds.
好吧？他们在艰难的局面中奋战。
They had no army. Hannibal was the greatest general in human history.
他们没有军队。汉尼拔是人类历史上最伟大的将军。
He had a huge army. But
他拥有庞大军队。
the Roman people were willing to make all the necessary sacrifices in order to protect their identity
罗马人民愿意做一切必要的牺牲，以守护他们的身份
and their values and their history.
以及他们的价值观与历史。
They refused that Rome fall.
他们拒绝让罗马落败。
So every person, whether it's woman,
于是每个人，无论男女，
man, or child, would have taken arms and
人或孩童会举起武器，抵御汉尼拔的进攻。
defended the city against Hannibal.
And this was really the highlight
这正是共和制度的亮点。
of the republican system.
It refuses to surrender.
它不投降。
Because to surrender would mean abandoning its identity.
投降就等于放弃自身身份。
Okay? So
好的？所以
that's why Rome was able to defeat all its enemies.
这就是罗马能打败所有敌人的原因。
Because the Roman idea of citizenship was flexible.
因为罗马的公民观念很灵活。
If you're willing to fight for Rome, you could become a citizen.
如果你愿意为罗马而战，你就能成为公民。
And as such,
于是，罗马就能召集士兵。
Rome was able to draw soldiers
Rome was able todraw soldiers
from all the Italian peninsula.
来自整个意大利半岛。
From 280 to 272 BCE,
从公元前280年到公元前272年，
there's something called the Pyrrhic Wars.
有一场被称为皮尔修战争的事。
Pyrrhus, who was a Greek king,
皮尔修是希腊王，
came to the aid of the Greek king, and he was able to build the Greek colonies in Italy.
他来援助希腊王，并能在意大利建起希腊殖民。
These Greeks were complaining and saying, the Romans are bullying us.
这些希腊人抱怨说，罗马欺压我们。
Can someone please help us and build us a Greek empire?
有人能帮我们建个希腊帝国吗？
So Pyrrhus comes and
于是皮尔修来临，
attacks the Romans.
他向罗马发动进攻。
And he won every battle.
他赢得每一场战斗。
The Romans were terrible soldiers.
罗马人是了不起的士兵。
He had the best soldiers in the world.
他拥有世界上最好的士兵。
And he was winning every battle. And
他赢得每一场战斗。并且
at a certain point, Pyrrhus said, OK,
在某个时点，皮尔修说，好吧，
we're killing a lot of Romans.
我们正在杀死不少罗马人。
But if I win one more battle, if I just win one more battle,
但如果我再赢一场战斗，我再赢一场战斗，我就要没兵了。
I'm going to run out of soldiers.
于是他就撤退了。
So he had to retreat. OK?
OK？
And this is because of the idea of citizenship.
这正是公民观念的缘起。
The Greeks could not replenish their forces, whereas the Romans could.
希腊人无法补充兵力，而罗马人则能。
OK? And
好吧？
this is what allowed for social mobility and innovation in Rome.
这使罗马实现社会流动与创新。
The fact that Rome was constantly fighting these battles,
罗马不断与各方交战，正是如此。
these wars against everyone, and
这些战争与各方对抗，正是如此。
learning from their mistakes, and growing as a military power.
从错误中学习，逐步壮大为军力。
Eventually, Rome comes in conflict with Carthage.
最终，罗马与迦特拉相冲突。
And Carthage is, at this point,
此时，迦特拉已是……
the greatest naval power of the Mediterranean.
地中海的最大海权
Rome did not have a navy.
罗马没有海军
It doesn't know how to sell ships.
它不知道怎么卖船
Guess what happened? They decided to build a navy.
猜猜发生了什么？他们决定建造海军。
And they lost all the battles against Carthage, again, because
又一次，他们在对阵迦特拉的战斗中全败。
Rome was so persistent.
因为罗马一直坚持不懈。
Because Rome was not afraid to lose soldiers.
因为罗马不怕失去士兵。
Eventually, it overwhelmed Carthage.
最终，它压倒了迦特拉。
OK? So
好的？
this is the reason why, eventually,
这就是原因，最终，
Rome was able to
罗马得以
conquer the entire Mediterranean world.
征服整个地中海世界。
No one could stop Rome.
没有人能阻止罗马。
OK? So by about 200 BCE,
好吧？大约在公元前200年，
Rome was the greatest military hegemon of that time.
罗马是当时最强大的陆权霸权。
And by about 100 BCE, 100 years later, it was an empire.
大约在公元前100年，100年后，它已成为帝国。
OK? So, are you guys clear?
好吧？那么，你们明白了吗？
Any questions so far before I continue?
到此为止，继续之前请问有无疑问？
Are you guys clear about this? All right.
你们明白了吗？好的。
But there's a problem when Rome became an empire.
但当罗马成为帝国时出现了问题。
A republic is not the same as a country.
共和国不等于一个国家。
It's not the same as an empire. An empire needed a bureaucracy.
它不等于帝国。帝国需要官僚。
It needed an emperor.
它需要一位皇帝。
You need a top -down system.
你需要自上而下的制度。
And that's in conflict with the idea of a republic,
而这与共和国的理念相冲突，
where you have to obey the history and the institutions.
在共和国里，你必须遵循历史与制度。
If you're an empire, you have to absorb new people into your culture.
若是帝国，则需把新民纳入自身文化。
But the Romans didn't want to do that, because it meant giving up their own culture.
但罗马人不想这么做，因为那意味着放弃自己的文化。
Right? So this created a contradiction.
对吧？于是产生了矛盾。
This created a paradox. And
这就形成了一个悖论。
this will eventually lead to a series of civil wars
这最终会导致一系列内战
that really never stops until Rome collapses.
那场内战一直持续到罗马崩溃为止
All right? So, to understand this idea, think about America today.
好了？要理解这个概念，想想今天的美国。
America, again,
美国，再次，
it is the...
它是……
It is humanity's greatest empire.
它是人类最大的帝国。
It controls the entire world, basically.
它基本上控制了整个世界。
It has 800 military bases around the world.
它在全球拥有800个军事基地。
China has about two.
中国大约有两个。
Okay? It has no peer competitor.
好的？它没有同级竞争者。
But there's one thing that you cannot say about America.
但有一件事你们说不出关于美国的。
If you go to America and say you guys are an empire,
如果你去美国说你们是帝国，
you'll be shut down.
你会被关闭。
How dare you say we're an empire?
你敢说我们是帝国？
There's nothing imperial about us.
我们没有帝国气息。
We're a republic. We're a democracy.
我们是共和国。我们是民主国家。
We're not an empire. For whatever reason,
我们不是帝国。无论何因，
Americans refuse to believe they're an empire.
美国人却不肯承认自己是帝国。
It's ridiculous. And you have some silly things.
真是可笑。你还有些傻瓜的说法。
For example, when Americans talk about the Middle East, right?
比如说，美国人谈到中东时，没错吧？
Clearly, America wants to control the Middle East for its resources.
显然，美国想掌控中东的资源。
But when you talk to American academics,
但当你对美国学者说话时，
American people, for whatever reason,
美国人，何因而如此，
they believe American Middle East policy is being controlled by Israel,
他们认为美国的中东政策被以色列掌控
a nation of 8 million people in a desert.
一个拥有800万人的沙漠民族。
Israel is able to control the American empire.
以色列能掌控美帝国。
And you're like, that makes no sense.
你说这点没道理。
Like, how is it possible for Israel to control America?
像，怎么可能以色列掌控美国？
But Americans really believe this. If you...
但美国人真的这么相信。如果你……
When you talk about the war in Ukraine,
谈到乌克兰战争时，
there are a lot of Americans who believe that it's the Europeans
有很多美国人认为是欧洲人让美国……
who are making America...
……让美国……
a cist -Ukraine.
……乌克兰。
It's all European...
全是欧洲的……
manipulation. And it's the silliest thing.
操纵而已，最可笑的事。
It's like, what are you talking about?
就像，你说的是什么？
The Europeans are a vassal state of America.
欧洲人是美国的附庙国。
Israel is a vassal state of America.
以色列是美国的附庙国。
And the reason why is Americans cannot understand
原因是美国人不懂。
that they're an empire. Because
那是因为他们是帝国。因为
it goes against their idea of themselves as democracy,
它与他们把自己视为民主、共和国的想法相冲突。
as a republic. All right?
好了？
This is what we call... The word for this is called
这就是我们所说的……这个词叫做
cognitive dissonance. All right?
认知失调。好吗？
You guys should have studied this in psychology, okay?
你们应该在心理学里学过这个，行吗？
But it's impossible to...
但这就不可能了……
for your mind to hold in place two contradictory ideas.
让你脑中同时容纳两个相互矛盾的概念。
America cannot both be a republic and an empire.
美国既是共和国又是帝国，根本不可能。
Therefore, it's a republic.
于是，它是个共和国。
And don't ever mention the word empire.
别再提“帝国”这个词。
Okay? And guess what?
好？你猜怎么了？
The Romans have the same...
罗马人也有同样的困境……
problem. They could not conceive of themselves as an empire.
他们没能把自己想成帝国。
And they refused to be an empire even though they were an empire.
即便是帝国，他们也不愿意当成帝国。
And this led to lots of civil wars
于是引发了许多内战
and conflicts between Rome and the people around Rome.
以及罗马与周边人民的冲突。
Okay? So the example is that
好的？这就是例子。
from 91 to 89,
从91年到89年
Rome fought something called the Social War.
罗马发动了被称为社会战争的战役
Remember, this is after Rome became...
记住，这发生在罗马成为…之后
an empire. It now has no...
一个帝国。它现在没有…
pair competitor. It has no adversary.
一对竞争者。它没有对手。
So now it starts to fight wars among its own people.
于是它开始在自己内部打战争。
The Social War was fought between Rome and
社会战争是罗马与…之间的战役
its Italian allies or neighbors.
它的意大利盟友或邻居。
For most of its history,
在其历史的大部分里。
Rome was drawing soldiers from its allies.
罗马从其盟友中调集士兵。
And after Rome became an empire,
随后罗马成为帝国。
its allies, Italian allies,
意大利盟友，
rightfully said, listen, we fought for you for decades.
正当说，听着，我们为你们战斗了几十年。
We've lost many men. We demand to be given citizenship.
我们失去了许多士兵。我们要求获得公民身份。
And Rome said no.
罗马答曰：不
And so they fought a civil war.
于是他们发动了内战。
And Rome lost the civil war because guess what?
于是罗马在内战中失利，猜猜为什么？
Its military was from the Italian peninsula.
其军队来自意大利半岛。
Okay? So it could not defeat its allies and so it had to make its allies
好的？于是它无法击败盟友，于是它又要让盟友成为自己的盟友
into Roman citizens.
成为罗马公民。
Okay? And Rome will keep on doing this.
好吧？罗马还会继续这么做。
Where it has all these subject people and
它拥有这些主体人群，并且这些主体人群会起义求公民。
subject people rebel because they want citizenship.
But again, for Rome,
但再说一次，关于罗马，
what matters is the protection of its cultural identity.
重要的是保护其文化身份。
And if you give citizenship to too many people, that dilutes your cultural identity.
如果把公民给太多人，文化身份就会被稀释。
They were afraid that Rome will stop being Rome.
他们担心罗马会失去罗马本身。
And that led to conflicts throughout its history.
并导致其历史上不断的冲突。
And it never really ended.
并且从未曾真正结束。
Okay? So
好的？所以
you can't ever use the word empire or emperor in Rome.
你在罗马里永远不能用“帝国”或“皇帝”这两个词。
Then the question then is, wait,
然后问题是，等一下，
wasn't Augustus Caesar
亚古斯都·凯撒不是吗？
after the Battle of Actium the first Roman emperor?
战后，第一位罗马皇帝是谁？
No. Okay?
不。好的吗？
The idea of an empire, the idea of an emperor, the idea
帝国、皇帝的概念
that Augustus Caesar was the first emperor is something that later started to be decided on by historians.
那亚古斯都·凯撒是第一位皇帝的说法，后来才被史学家确定。
The Romans did not see themselves as an empire.
罗马人自认为不是一个帝国。
And Augustus Caesar did not see himself as an emperor.
亚古斯都·凯撒也不认为自己是皇帝。
The word he used, the word the Romans used, is the idea of precept.
他使用的词，罗马人使用的词，就是预设的概念。
Okay? Preceptus means in Latin,
好的？预设在拉丁语里是指……
first citizen. We are still equals, meaning senators.
先民。我们仍是平等的，指的是参议员。
Okay? But I'm just a bit better than you.
好的？我只是比你稍好一点。
I'm the first among equals.
我是同等之中第一。
Okay? And
好的？
this is where we get the English word prince from.
这就是我们得到英文单词“prince”的地方。
And Augustus Caesar did not see himself as building an empire.
而奥古斯都·凯撒并没有把自己视为建造帝国的人。
He saw himself as saving the republic.
他把自己视为拯救共和国的人。
Okay? Now,
好吧？现在，
I'm going to tell you that I'm not going to tell you party party party party party party party
我要告诉你，我不会再说“派对派对派对派对派对派对”了
party party party party party
派对派对派对派对
party party party party party party party party party party party party
派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对
party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party
派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派对派
party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party
派对派对
party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party party
And so they allowed his heir,
于是他们允许他的继承人，
his son, to be king or emperor without much opposition.
他的儿子，顺利登基为王或皇帝。
That was not true
那并不是真的
for his
为他的
heirs.
继承人
So after Augustus Caesar died,
于是，奥古斯都凯撒去世后，
all the civil wars and conflicts that
所有的内战和冲突
were suppressed were now fomented again.
被压制的又重新被挑起。
And this would now lead to a massive period of civil wars.
这又将导致一段大规模的内战时期。
Now, our understanding of Roman history comes
现在，我们对罗马历史的理解主要来自罗马史学家本身。
a lot from Roman historians themselves.
随后我们基本听从他们所写的。
Specifically two individuals, Livy and Tacitus.
具体有两位人物，利维和塔西佗。
And we basically listened to what they wrote.
我们基本听从他们所写的。
For example, we...
例如，我们……
So what we wrote was, What we mean by that is, we take their word as gospel.
于是我们写下来的，就是我们所说的那句话，我们把他们的话当作圣言。
We take the word as truth.
我们把词当作真理。
But what we need to recognize is they were senators,
但我们需要认识的是他们是参议员。
part of the nobility, who hated the emperors,
部分贵族，他们恨皇帝，
who hated the princeps.
他们恨首领。
So they did whatever they could in order to make the emperors look bad.
于是他们做了任何能让皇帝显得糟糕的事。
So there were four emperors...
于是出现了四位皇帝……
Sorry, there were three emperors after the death of Augustus.
抱歉，奥古斯都去世后，实际上只有三位皇帝。
Augustus, Tiberius, Caligula, and Nero.
奥古斯都、提伯、卡利古拉和尼禄。
And they were all made to look very, very bad.
他们被刻意塑造成非常非常糟糕的形象。
Especially Nero and Caligula.
尤其是尼禄和卡利古拉。
And Tiberius.
而提伯。
Okay? So,
好？于是，
let me give you an example of this.
让我给你举个例子。
So, after Augustus dies,
于是，奥古斯都去世后，
Augustus names two people
奥古斯都任命两人
here to his legacy.
继承其遗志
Okay? The first is Tiberius, who
好？第一位是提伯里乌斯，他成为皇帝。
becomes the emperor.
提伯里乌斯不是他的儿子。
Tiberius is not his son.
Tiberius is nothis son.
It is his adopted son.
它是他的养子。
Okay? So that is a Roman tradition where
好？这就是罗马的传统，能把家族外的人收为继承。
you can adopt someone outside the family to be your heir.
And then, after Tiberius died,
随后，提伯里乌斯去世后，
Augustus anointed Germanicus to be his successor. And
奥古斯都为德国人加冕为继任者。随后
Germanicus was considered an extremely talented
德国人被视为极具才华的
and capable leader. Okay?
并且是能干的领袖。好？
The problem, though, is that
问题是
Tiberius, who is now emperor,
提伯里乌斯，现在是皇帝，
didn't like the fact that
不喜欢这个事实
Germanicus was appointed his successor.
德国人被任命为继任者。
He wanted to anoint his own successor.
他想任命自己的继任者。
Okay? So Tiberius, what he did
好？于是提伯里乌斯，他所做的事是
that was very sneaky was...
那件非常诡计的事是…
He got...
他做了…
He made a man named Sejanus
他任命一名叫塞贾努斯的人
the head
为帕雷托里安卫队的首领
of the Praetorian Guard.
And the Praetorian Guard was basically the secret police of Rome.
帕雷托里安卫队基本上就是罗马的秘密警察。
And Sejanus, because he was very ambitious,
塞贾努斯因为很有野心，开始……
he started to kill not just Germanicus, but
他开始杀人不止于盖尔尼乌斯，还……
everyone in Germanicus' family.
在盖尔尼乌斯的家族里，人人都被杀。
Sejanus wanted to be the heir to Tiberius.
塞贾努斯想成为提伯里乌斯的继承人。
And then after Sejanus was done killing everyone,
随后塞贾努斯把所有人都杀完后，
basically in Germanicus' family,
基本上在盖尔尼乌斯的家族里
Tiberius had him killed.
提伯里乌斯让他被杀
Okay? This is a very common pattern in imperial history.
好吧？这在帝国史上很常见的模式
Okay? After Sejanus was killed,
好吧？塞贾努斯被杀后，
there's a purge of Sejanus' allies.
随后是对塞贾努斯盟友的清洗。
His children were killed, and everyone who
他的子孙被杀，所有人都…
supports Sejanus was interrogated by the Senate and put to death.
塞贾努斯得到支持后被参议院讯问并处死。
And most of these people claim innocence.
这些人中大多数人自称无罪。
I had nothing to do with Sejanus.
我与塞贾努斯无关。
I was forced into an alliance with Sejanus.
我被迫与塞贾努斯结盟。
Okay? Now, there's one person,
好吧？现在，有一个人，
a Roman nobleman named Marcus Tarantius,
一位名叫马库斯·塔兰提乌斯的罗马贵族。
who in 31 CE,
谁在31年出现，
he appeared before the Senate for his trial.
他在参议院受审判。
And he decided on a different strategy.
于是他采取了另一种策略。
Everyone else before him claimed, I had nothing to do with Sejanus.
其他人都说，我和塞贾努斯没关系。
And the Senate didn't believe them.
参议院也不相信他们。
And they were all killed. Okay?
他们都被杀了。
So, Marcus Tarantius tries a different strategy.
于是，马库斯·塔兰提乌斯采用了另一种策略。
And this is recounted in the history book,
这件事在历史书中被记载，公元一百年后，塔西佗在《编年史》中写下。
Annals, by Tacitus, who is writing about 100 years later.
Okay? And this is what Marcus Tarantius argues.
好的？这就是马库斯·塔兰提乌斯的论点。
He argues, Yes,
他这么说，嗯，
I was his friend.
我是他的朋友。
In fact, I tried very best to be his friend.
实际上，我尽力成为他的朋友。
Why? Because Sejanus had the favor of the emperor.
为什么？因为塞贾努得了皇帝的青睐。
Because if I wanted to get anything done, if I wanted to become wealthy,
因为若我想办事、致富，
I had to become a friend of Sejanus.
我必须成为塞贾努的朋友。
And why did I do this?
我为什么这么做？
And why was this right? Because
为什么这件事是对的？因为
it is not up to me to
这事不由我决定
question or think about why Sejanus is a friend of the emperor.
去问或思考塞贾努为何是皇帝的朋友
All I need to know was the emperor favored Sejanus.
我只需知道皇帝青睐塞贾努
And it is my duty to obey the emperor.
并且我有义务服从皇帝。
And therefore, I became his friend.
于是我便成为他的朋友。
Okay? That was his logic.
好吧？那就是他的逻辑。
Now, let's look at what Tacitus wrote.
现在，让我们看看塔西佗写的内容。
Okay? And it's really one of the most
好吧？这真的是历史上最精彩的段落之一。
striking paragraphs in the history.
Okay? But this is Marcus Tarantius' defense of himself before the Senate
好吧？但这就是马库斯·塔兰提乌斯在参议院前为自己辩护的陈述。
and the emperor.
和皇帝。
It is not ours to ask whom you,
这不是我们问你是谁的事。
the emperor, exalt above the king.
皇帝，凌驾于王之上。
Or why you, the gods, have made sovereign arbiter of things.
或者你们，众神，为何把万事的主宰定为你们？
Okay? It is not my place to ever question the emperor.
好吧？这不是我问皇帝的事。
If the emperor made Sejanus his right -hand man,
如果皇帝把塞贾努斯任为右手人。
I now must also obey Sejanus.
我现在也必须服从塞贾努斯。
If the emperor wants me to marry a dog, I will go marry a dog.
如果皇帝让我嫁给一只狗，我就去嫁给一只狗。
To search to us has been left the glory of obedience.
寻找我们已被赋予的服从荣耀。
To search out the hidden thoughts of the emperor and
寻找皇帝隐藏思绪的方式
the designs he may shape in secret is unlawful and dangerous.
他可能在暗中构思的设计是非法且危险的。
Nor would the searcher necessarily find.
也不必然找到
Okay? What does this mean? It means the emperor is God.
好的？这是什么意思？就是皇帝是上帝。
He has a secret design.
他有一个秘密设计。
He has a secret logic that we could never know.
他有一个我们永远知道不了的秘密逻辑。
And because we're too stupid.
因为我们太笨了。
And if we try to figure it out,
如果我们试着弄清楚它，
we're breaking the laws of Rome and the universe.
我们正打破罗马与宇宙的法则。
And we could only get into trouble.
于是我们才会陷入麻烦。
So it's not up to me to question the emperor.
所以这事不由我来问皇帝。
It is only my duty to obey the emperor.
只要服从皇帝即是我的职责。
The firmness of this speech.
这段演讲的坚定性。
Okay? So he's finished speaking, defending himself in front of the Senate.
好的？于是他在参议院前完成发言，辩护自己。
And this is how the emperor and the Senate respond to this speech.
而这就是皇帝和参议院对这段演讲的回应。
The firmness of this speech.
这段演讲的坚定性。
He speaks with conviction. Okay?
他讲话很有说服力。好吗？
And the fact that
并且
a man had been discovered to utter what the world was thinking.
有人被发现能说出世界的想法。
Made so powerful an impression that
使其印象如此强大，以致
his accusers were penalized by banishment or death.
其指控者被流放或处死
Okay? So rather than punish this man,
好的？于是把这人放过来，而不是惩罚他。
the Senate punished his accusers.
于是参议院惩罚了他的指控者。
His enemies. Why?
他的敌人。为什么？
Because they had found a man to speak the truth about the world.
因为他们发现了一个能说出世界真相的人。
The emperor was in command.
皇帝掌权在手。
We had to obey the emperor.
我们必须服从皇帝。
And they wanted to make a role model out of him.
于是他们把他当作榜样。
And therefore, they killed all his enemies and let him go.
于是他们杀死了他的所有敌人，让他离开。
And rewarded him lavishly.
并丰厚奖赏他。
Okay? Now,
好的？现在，
this was written in
这写在
contrast to Roman history.
与罗马历史形成对照。
This marks a radical departure from Roman history.
这标志着罗马历史的根本转折。
Remember. In 509,
记住。509年，
the Republic was founded.
共和国成立。
Because they threw out the king. In response,
因为他们把国王赶走。
the king organized his allies, the Etruscans, and they marched on Rome. And
国王召集其盟友伊特鲁斯坎人，率军进罗马。随后
Rome was surrounded by a huge army.
罗马被一支庞大军队包围。
And there was nothing Rome could do about it.
于是罗马对此无能为之。
So a young nobleman
于是有一位年轻贵族人。
named Musius went to the senators.
名为穆西乌斯的他去见参议员。
And proposed a daring plan to assassinate the king.
并提出大胆的计划，暗杀国王。
He swims across the Tiber.
他游过台伯河。
He goes into the camp of the enemy.
他进入敌军营地。
And he's captured. He's interrogated by the king.
他被俘获，随后被国王讯问。
And Musius says, we Romans have sworn to kill all kings.
于是穆西乌斯说：我们罗马人已发誓要杀死所有国王。
And to show that he's serious, he puts his hand into a fire.
并且为示其真诚，他把手伸进火中。
And he burns his hand in front of the king.
他在国王面前把手烫了。
And the king is scared.
于是国王惊慌。
So he runs away.
于是他跑开了。
Okay? So
好的？那么
this story shows us the nature of the Roman character.
这件事让我们看到了罗马人的性格
Romans hate kings.
罗马人爱国王？
Romans will always disobey kings.
Romans will always find a way to kill kings.
罗马人总会想办法杀掉国王。
And this speech shows us that
这段演讲让我们看到这一点。
the Roman character has fundamentally changed because of empire.
罗马人的性格因帝国而根本改变。
Okay? So
好的吗？那么
Romans throughout most of its history,
罗马人在其历史的大部分里，
the Roman people have been grappling with what it means to be Roman.
罗马人民一直在思考何为罗马人。
And how to protect this precious identity.
以及如何保护这份珍贵的身份。
Now, we know that
现在，我们知道了。
even though Tacitus wrote this,
即便塔西佗写下这点，
the Roman identity didn't really change.
罗马人的身份并未真正改变。
How do we know this? How do we know
我们怎么知道呢？
that even though Tacitus says, okay, empire changed.
即便塔西佗说，帝国确已变迁。
The Roman identity.
罗马身份。
It didn't really change. How do we know this?
它并未真正变迁。我们怎么知道呢？
Because he's writing about this, right?
因为他在写这件事，对吧？
He's writing about this. He's telling us
他在写这件事。他告诉我们
that the Roman identity changed because of empire.
罗马身份因帝国而改变
Well, if the Roman identity really changed, people wouldn't know it changed.
好吧，如果罗马身份真的改变，民众就会知道它改变了。
It's only because people are resisting the change in nature.
只是因为民众在抵抗性格的变化。
The change in character.
性格的变化。
That people appreciate what Tacitus is writing.
人们欣赏塔西佗所写的内容。
And Tacitus is really saying
塔西佗实际上在说：
that, oh, that empire,
那，哦，那帝国，
it's gone now.
它已经过去了。
Because the new emperor has restored the republic.
因为新皇帝恢复了共和国。
Okay? So throughout its history,
好吧？所以在它的历史中，
Rome was causing a battle between empire and republic.
罗马引发帝国与共和国之间的战斗。
And every new emperor believed that
每位新皇帝都认为自己在恢复共和国。
he was restoring the republic.
他认为自己在恢复共和国。
But then someone else would come along and say, no, he was the dictator.
但随后又有人出现，接着说，没错，他是独裁者。
He was the emperor. Okay?
他是皇帝。好吧？
So this was a conflict throughout Roman history.
这就是罗马历史上的一次冲突。
And so now the question, we go on to the second question, which is, alright,
于是现在问题来了，接着第二个问题，嗯，怎么说，
how did the empire fall?
帝国是怎么倒下来的？
Okay. Well, the standard explanation is that.
好吧。一般的解释是这样：
That eventually, Rome became too corrupt.
最终，罗马变得太腐败。
And this is the explanation provided by most Roman historians.
这就是大多数罗马史家给出的解释。
As well as the famous British historian,
以及著名英史家，
Edward Gibbon, in his most famous work,
爱德华·吉本在他最著名的著作中，
History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire.
《罗马帝国衰落史》。”
Okay? It's corruption.
好吧？是腐败。
It's because the Romans became more like the Greeks or like the Persians.
它是因为罗马人变得更像希腊人或波斯人。
They started to appreciate the luxury.
他们开始欣赏奢靡。
Deconance and corruption of empire more.
帝国的衰落与腐败更甚。
Okay? And the explanation is
好的？解释是
that over time,
随着时间的推移，
you had all these dramatic invaders from the steppes.
你会遇到这些来自草原的戏剧性入侵者。
Remember the steppes is where the Yemnaya people come from.
记住草原是耶姆纳雅人起源之地。
These Visigoths are being pushed up by the Huns.
维西哥特人被匈奴推上去。
Okay? So
好吧？
remember the steppes is really
记住草原真是
this massive competitive whirlpool hurricane.
这大规模的竞争漩涡飓风。
That makes people more and more aggressive.
这让人们越来越激进。
And more aggressive tribes will push out less aggressive tribes.
更具侵略性的部落会把不那么侵略的部落推开。
And these people are forced to go into Europe.
这些人被迫迁入欧洲。
And over time,
随着时间推移，
the Romans are trying to absorb them into their empire.
罗马人正试图把他们吸纳进帝国。
By making them soldiers or by giving them land.
把他们做成士兵或给他们土地。
Okay? But over time,
对吧？但随着时间推移，
this pure population will force the empire to collapse.
这纯粘人群将迫使帝国崩溃。
Okay? And that's the standard explanation.
对吧？这就是常规解释。
I want to make a different argument.
我想提出另一种论点。
My argument is this.
我的论点是这个。
It really has to do again with the idea of citizenship and identity.
它确实又要回到公民身份与身份认同的概念上。
Throughout most of its history,
在其大部分历史中，
imperial Rome has been struggling with this identity issue.
帝国罗马正为此身份问题而苦恸。
And then at some point, an emperor came along and said, screw this.
随后某位皇帝登场，宣言：搞这事吧。
We no longer want to be a republic.
我们不再想做共和国了。
We want to be an empire. Okay?
我们想成为一个帝国。好吗？
And the way you can resolve this issue is in 212,
解决这个问题的办法是在212年，
the emperor Caracalla issued the Edict of Caracalla, which
皇帝卡拉卡拉发布了卡拉卡拉诏书，
made everyone in Roman Empire a citizen.
让罗马帝国的每个人都成为公民。
So he basically destroyed the idea of citizenship.
于是他基本上消灭了公民的概念。
If everyone can be a citizen, citizenship means nothing.
若人人皆为公民，公民又何意义？
Before, you had to fight for Rome.
在之前，你必须为罗马而战。
You had to die for Rome in order to become a citizen.
你必须为罗马而死，才能成为公民。
You had to believe in the customs, the history.
你必须相信习俗与历史。
The tradition of Rome to become a citizen.
罗马成为公民的传统。
You had to fight for it.
你必须为此而战。
It was valuable.
它很有价值。
In fact, it was the most valuable thing in the world for people.
实际上，它是人们在世界上最有价值的东西。
But now everyone got it.
但现在每个人都拥有了它。
So it was absolutely worthless. Okay?
于是它就变得完全没价值了。
And because everyone was now a Roman citizen,
于是每个人都成为罗马公民，于是罗马身份消失。
there was now no more Roman identity.
于是罗马身份消失。
It was now a clean slate.
The emperors were now no longer bounded by tradition or history.
皇帝们现在不再受传统或历史束缚。
Okay? They were now ruled by institutions like the Senate.
好了？他们现在由诸如参议院的机构统治。
And so now they could build the imperial bureaucracy.
于是他们便能建立帝国官僚体系。
And this imperial bureaucracy will replace the Republic.
于是这套帝国官僚体系将取代共和国。
And the major change is in 330,
而主要变化发生在330年，
the emperor Constantine will move the capital from Rome
皇帝康斯坦丁将首都从罗马迁至…
to a place called Byzantium, which
迁至名为拜占庭的地方，随后成为拜占庭帝国或东罗马帝国。
will become the Byzantine Empire or the Eastern Roman Empire.
好了？我们下节课再聊。
Okay? We'll talk about this next class.
But this is something that was unthinkable.
但这件事曾是不可思议的。
How could you move the heart and center and
你怎么能把帝国的心脏、中心和灵魂从罗马迁到别处？这真是不可思议的。
soul of the empire from Rome to somewhere else? It was unthinkable.
If to be Roman
若是罗马人
was meant to die for Rome, but now the capital was somewhere else.
若是罗马人，意味着为罗马而死，但现在首都已迁至他处。
Okay? And so
好了？
this marks basically the
这基本标志着罗马的文化身份结束。
end of Rome as a cultural identity.
作为文化灯塔。
As a cultural beacon.
Okay? This marked really the death of the history of Rome.
好的？这确实标志着罗马历史的终结。
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys? Okay?
好的？这对你们来说有道理吗？好的？
Now, historians argue about this.
现在，历史学家们就此展开争论。
And historians argue when the Roman Empire fell.
历史学家们争论罗马帝国何时崩溃。
All right? But the consensus is 476 when
好吧？但共识是公元476年，德国战士推翻最后一位皇帝罗慕鲁斯·奥古斯都。
a German warlord deposed the last emperor named Romulus Augustus.
在公元212年，罗马宣布人人皆可为公民。
Okay? But I disagree. I believe that it really happened.
好的？但我不这么认为。我认为它真的发生了。
It happened in 212 when
它发生在212年，当时
Rome announced everyone could be a citizen.
罗马宣布人人皆可为公民。
Okay? And we'll talk more about this next class
好的？我们下节课再聊这件事
when we get to the Byzantine Empire.
等到拜占庭帝国时再说
And, okay? So any questions so far?
好的？到此为止，先问问有无疑问
I know this is a lot, but
我知道这有点多，但……
we'll try to clarify a lot of the issues over the next few classes.
我们将在接下来的几节课里尝试把这些问题弄清楚。
Okay? But if you have any questions now, please ask.
好了？如果现在有任何问题，请提出来。
Any questions so far about this?
到此为止，先问问有无疑问？
Is this clear to you guys?
这清楚吗？
Yeah? So I'm wondering if Tassidus was a citizen.
嗯？我想知道Tassidus是公民吗？
Tassidus. Tassidus died.
塔西杜斯。塔西杜斯去世。
So, like, he was going to be following the emperor.
于是，他将跟随皇帝。
So, he was poor.
他很贫穷。
So, in the empire.
于是，在帝国里。
Okay. Let me clear this.
好的。让我来澄清。
Tassidus was a senator.
塔西杜斯是参议员。
Okay? The senator was always in conflict with the emperor.
好的？参议员总是与皇帝争斗。
The senate, okay, sorry, let me clarify about the senate.
参议院，好吧，抱歉，我来澄清参议院。
The senate was basically the Roman aristocracy.
参议院基本是罗马贵族。
It was where the ruling families of Rome sat.
它是罗马统治家族聚集的地方。
And they were supposed to be in charge of the empire.
他们本应掌管帝国。
And the emperor was basically the CEO, okay?
皇帝基本是首席执行官，明白吗？
He was basically in charge of managing the empire.
他基本负责管理帝国。
But it was the senate that was supposed to make the decisions.
但本应由参议院作决策。
In reality, it was the emperor who was in charge because
实际上是皇帝掌管。
the emperor controlled the army and he controlled the bataring guard, which was the secret police.
皇帝掌管军队，他也掌管班塔里卫队，即秘密警察。
So he could kill senators who disobeyed him, okay?
于是他可以杀死不服从的参议员，明白吗？
And this was always a very complex relationship.
这始终是一段非常复杂的关系。
So when Tacitus, again, who is a senator,
于是当塔西佗再次出现，他是参议员，
who comes from one of the elite families of Rome,
他来自罗马的贵族家族之一，
when he's writing about the history of the
当他写下罗马历史时，
Roman Empire from the time of Augustus to Nero,
罗马帝国从奥古斯都到尼禄的时代
he's trying to paint them in a very bad light.
他正试着把他们描绘得很糟糕
Okay? Because he's trying to tell us, emperors are bad.
好吧？因为他想告诉我们，皇帝是坏的
What's good is the senate. And
好的事是参议院。还有
that's why he's producing this speech.
这就是他发表这篇演讲的原因。
Because if you're a Roman citizen and
因为如果你是罗马公民并且
you read this speech by Marcus Tyrannus, you are appalled.
你读了马库斯·提尔纳斯的演讲，便惊叹。
You're disgusted. We're Romans.
你感到惊叹。我们是罗马人。
We hate kings. We do not obey.
我们恨王。我们不服从。
We fight. We do not surrender.
我们战斗。我们不投降。
Okay? So this speech goes against the very heart
好了？这段演讲正是针对罗马人之心魂的。
and soul of what it means to be Roman.
And that's why Tacitus is writing this.
这就是塔西图斯写这篇文章的原因。
He's saying, you see what empire does to the Roman character.
他在说，你看帝国对罗马人的性格所做的事。
It corrupts us.
它使我们腐化。
It destroys us. It weakens us.
它把我们毁掉。它把我们削弱。
And therefore we must resist the emperor and protect the senate.
于是我们要抵御皇帝，保卫参议院。
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
好的？这样说通吗，大家？
Okay. So thanks for that.
好的。谢谢。
Okay? So I apologize because
好的？所以我道歉。
I'm running through a lot of history in a short amount of time, so I'm missing a lot of important details.
我在短时间内梳理了大量历史，所以遗漏了许多重要细节。
What's really important for you to understand is, in a republic,
对你来说真正重要的是，在共和国里…
the senate is in charge.
参议院掌管。
Okay? Meaning the ruling houses.
好的吗？意思是统治家族。
The aristocracy is in charge. But in an empire,
贵族掌管。但在帝国里，
the emperor is in charge.
皇帝掌管。
But Rome never resolved this issue.
但罗马从未解决这个问题。
Who should be in charge? The senate or the emperor?
谁应该掌管？参议院还是皇帝？
And it changes over time. Okay?
它会随时间变化。好吗？
Sometimes the senate is in charge.
有时参议院掌管。
Sometimes the emperor is in charge.
有时皇帝掌管。
But they all believe they're protecting the republic.
他们都认为自己是在保护共和国。
And this creates conic dissonance.
于是产生了圆锥不和谐。
Okay? And it creates a lot of confusion.
好了？又造成了大量混乱。
And then in 212, the emperor said, screw this, let's just be an empire.
然后在212年，皇帝说，搞什么，直接当个帝国吧。
I don't want the senate anymore. Okay?
我不想再有参议院了。
And this begins a process of creating the Byzantium Empire,
于是开始了创建拜占庭帝国的过程，
which does not have the idea of a Roman character.
它没有罗马式的特质。
Okay? Do you have a question, Echo?
好的？Echo，你有什么问题吗？
So basically, are the phoenixes, like, more sustainable?
所以，基本上，凤凰更可持续吗？
Exactly. Yeah.
完全对。嗯。
The senate is filled by, again, members of the ruling houses.
参议院再次由执政家族成员填充。
And what's interesting about this system is it's almost like a federal system.
而这个制度有趣的是，它几乎像一个联邦制度。
I'm not sure if you know what a federal system is.
我不确定你是否知道联邦制度是什么。
But the emperor is in charge of the army.
但皇帝负责军队。
And he's in charge of the secret police in Rome.
他还负责罗马的秘密警察。
But the senators are actually in charge of the provinces.
但参议员实际上负责各省。
So basically, each senator gets a certain province to control.
所以基本上，每位参议员都获得一个省份来掌管。
Okay? So it's like the United States, where governors are in charge of the provinces.
好的？所以它就像美国，州长负责各州。
And the president is in charge of the state. The president is in charge of the nation.
而总统负责州。总统负责国家。
Okay? Now, what's important for you to understand is,
好的？现在，重要的是你要理解的是，
technically, each state is independent.
技术上，每个州都是独立的。
Each state has its own army, has its own, basically, legal system.
每个州都有自己的军队，自己的，基本上，法律体系。
And it agrees to be part of the federal system, which the president is part of.
并且它同意成为联邦体系的一部分，联邦体系由总统组成。
And this is very similar to the Roman system.
这与罗马制度非常相似。
Okay? Not exactly, but it's very similar.
好？不完全一样，但很相近。
All right? Okay.
好的？明白了。
Any more questions? Any more questions before I conclude?
还有问题吗？我结束前还有别的问题吗？
Okay. So, my,
好的。那么，我，
the last question I want to look at today is,
今天我要看的最后一个问题是，
what's the legacy of the Roman Empire or the Republic?
罗马帝国或共和国的遗产是什么？
And the answer is, we still live in the Roman world.
答案是：我们仍然生活在罗马世界里。
Even though we like to think that
即使我们常想如此说…
we are heavily influenced by the Greeks.
我们受希腊影响很大。
It's institutions of Rome that we've inherited.
我们继承的是罗马的制度。
Okay? So,
好的？那么，
the idea of the political system,
政治制度的概念，
the legal system, the cultural system, it's something
法律制度、文化制度，它们是美国人基本复制粘贴的东西。
that the Americans basically copy and pasted.
The Roman system, the American system is very, very Roman.
罗马制度，咱们的制度非常非常罗马式。
And right now, of course, America controls the world.
现在正好，当然，美国掌控世界。
And therefore, it's able to disseminate Roman values
于是，它能传播罗马价值。
and culture. Okay?
和文化。好吗？
And throughout the semester,
在整个学期里，
we will be examining how Rome
我们将研究罗马
came to control the cultural framework of Western civilization.
它来掌控西方文明的文化框架。
Okay? Because even though Rome collapsed
好吗？因为即使罗马坍塌…
and Rome,
罗马，
the character of Rome is now dead,
罗马的形象已逝去，
the Roman legacy is still there.
罗马的遗产仍在，
And all these people fighting, these warlords,
这些争斗的将领们，
okay, these basically German warlords,
好的，这些基本上是德国将领们，
they're now going to fight the Civil War after the death of Rome.
他们现在将会在罗马去世后展开内战，
They're claiming to be carrying on the legacy of Rome.
他们声称自己是罗马遗产的延续。
Okay? From their perspective, Rome has not died.
好的？从他们的角度看，罗马并未消亡。
But Rome has spread out.
但罗马已经扩散。
And these warlords will adopt a lot of Roman practices.
这些将领将采纳大量罗马的做法。
And these warlords will build the culture
这些将领将建设文化
that will give rise to new nations called France,
这将孕育出新的民族国家——法国、德国、英国，基本上就是欧洲世界。
Germany, Britain, basically the European world.
Okay? So, that's the legacy of Rome.
好的？所以，这就是罗马的遗产。
That's why it's important to study Rome.
这就是研究罗马的重要性所在。
What lessons, okay,
什么教训，好的，
what lessons can we draw from Rome?
我们能从罗马学到什么教训？
Well, one really important lesson
好吧，最重要的教训之一是……
that we have to learn here is the idea of citizenship and identity.
我们必须学会的就是公民身份与身份感的概念。
You cannot be a strong
你若没有强大的文化，就不能成为一个强大而统一的民族国家。
and coherent nation if you do not have a strong culture.
你若没有强大的文化身份，就不能成为一个强大而统一的民族国家。那就是罗马人之所以如此的原因。
You cannot be a strong and coherent nation if you do not have a strong cultural identity. That's why the Romans were
那就是罗马人之所以如此的原因。
so insistent on protecting that
如此坚持保护那份身份
identity against the Greeks,
对抗希腊的身份
against foreigners.
对外来者的身份
Okay? And this is important because if you look at the Western world today,
好的？这很重要，因为如果你看看今天的西方世界，
immigration, identity,
移民、身份、
and citizenship are huge political issues.
以及公民身份都是大政治议题。
I'm a Canadian citizen.
我是加拿大公民。
I grew up in Canada.
我在加拿大长大。
And over the past ten years, the population has been growing.
过去十年里，人口一直在增长。
The population of Canada went from like 30 million to 40 million.
加拿大人口从约3000万增至4000万。
These ten million people are all foreigners
这多出的1000万都是外来人。
who have no sense of Canadian identity.
他们没有加拿大身份感。
They have no interest in being Canadian.
他们对成为加拿大人没有兴趣。
They just want a better life for themselves.
他们只是想为自己过更好的生活。
Forty percent of Canadians now were either
现在四十%的加拿大人是…
foreign born or have a parent who is a foreign born.
外生或父母为外生。
So there's no more Canadian identity.
于是就没有加拿大身份。
And this is a problem.
这就是问题所在。
Why? Because the United States, Trump,
为什么？因为美国，特朗普，
wants to take over Canada and
想接管加拿大并
make Canada into the 51st state.
把加拿大变成第51个州
Okay? And this is a problem because
好的？这就是问题所在。
Canadians don't want to resist against this.
加拿大人不想对此抗争。
Ten years ago, all Canadians would say, nope.
十年前，所有加拿大人都会说，没错。
But now you have ten million Canadians
但现在你有一千万加拿大人
who are very happy to join the United States because
他们非常高兴加入美国，因为
it means more economic opportunities for them.
这意味着更多的经济机会。
Right? They don't care about cultural identity.
对吧？他们不在乎文化身份。
So without controlling immigration,
于是若不控制移民，
you as a nation can't be coherent
作为一个民族国家，你们无法保持统一
and you will cease to exist over time.
并且你将随时间消失。
And the same is true of what's happening in Britain,
同样的情况也发生在英国
throughout the Western world basically.
在西方世界基本上。
They're landing too many immigrants and they're diluting their own cultural identity.
他们接收太多移民，导致自身文化身份被稀释。
So over the next ten, twenty years,
于是在接下十、二十年里，
a lot of people are predicting, maybe, that they're going to be able to live in Canada.
很多人预测，或许多人认为他们将能在加拿大生活。
And that's why we're seeing massive civil wars in
这就是我们看到大规模内战的原因
the Western world as these nations
西方世界如这些国家
grapple with the consequences of unlimited immigration these past ten years.
处理过去十年无限移民的后果
Okay? So that's one thing to think about.
好的？这就是一个值得思考的点。
One lesson that we can learn from the Roman world.
我们可以从罗马世界学到的一个教训。
Citizenship does matter.
公民身份很重要。
Make it hard to become a citizen.
让成为公民变得困难。
Make it valuable.
让它有价值。
Make it an honor to be a citizen.
让成为公民成为一种荣誉。
And your nation will be strong.
如果公民身份便宜，你的民族将会强大。
If citizenship is cheap.
如果公民身份便宜。
If you can just buy it, then it's worthless.
如果你能买到它，那就没价值。
And you will cease to be culturally coherent.
然后你将失去文化连贯性。
And eventually you will cease to exist as a nation.
于是你最终会失去民族国家的存在。
Okay? That's the first major lesson.
好的？这就是第一个主要教训。
Second major lesson about Rome is it won out
第二个主要教训是罗马之所以能赢是因为它是个进攻的民族。
because it was an aggressive nation.
But once you win out against your enemies,
但一旦你在敌人面前取胜，
this aggression has to go somewhere.
这种进攻必须有个出口。
And it usually turns inward.
并且它往往往
Okay? And that's why Rome kept on fighting these civil wars amongst itself.
好的？这就是罗马之所以一直在内战中奋战的原因。
And the same is true for America.
而同样的情况也适用于美国。
America is a nation that worships aggression.
美国是一个崇尚进攻的民族。
For example, think about the number of guns in America.
例如，想想美国的枪支数量。
There's like, I don't know the exact statistics, but
大约有四亿支枪在美国。
there's about 400 million guns in America.
美国大约有四亿支枪
America only has 200 million people.
美国只有两亿人
There are more guns than there are people in America.
美国的枪支数量多于人口。
It worships violence.
它崇尚暴力。
Also think about this.
也想想这个。
The most popular sport in America is American football.
美国最受欢迎的运动是美式足球。
There's only one nation in the world that plays American football, and that's America.
全世界只有一个国家玩美式足球，那就是美国。
No other nation plays it.
没有其他国家玩它。
Why? Because it is barbaric.
为什么？因为它是野蛮的。
You literally have people trying to kill each other for the entertainment
你们真的让人们互相杀戮来娱乐。
and pleasure of spectators.
和观众的乐趣。
It's barbaric. I'm not sure if you know this,
这很野蛮。我不确定你是否知道。
but after five years of fighting, the most people that play football,
但经过五年的战斗，踢球最多的人们，
these athletes, their brains are mush.
这些运动员，他们的脑袋全是糊糊的。
And they commit suicide at age 30 or 35.
他们在三十或三十五岁时自杀。
Okay? So
好的？所以
it's no different from gladiator sport in Rome,
它和罗马的角斗士运动没什么区别，
which Romans loved. Okay? So America is a violent society.
罗马人很喜欢。好的？所以美国是个暴力社会。
If it cannot turn its violence outside, it will turn violence,
如果它不能把暴力投向外部，它就会把暴力转向内部。
it will direct the violence and aggression inwards.
于是我认为在未来十年内，美国最有可能发动一场战争。
So I think within the next ten years, America will most likely start a war,
So I think within the next ten years,America will most likely start a war,
probably against Iran. Okay?
大概是对伊朗。好吗？
So I'm predicting within the next five years, America will start a war against Iran.
我预测在未来五年内，美国会对伊朗发动战争。
Probably sooner. And then America will start a civil war as well.
可能更早，然后美国也会发动内战。
So civil war does not mean two sides fighting against each other.
于是内战不只是两方互相对抗。
It just means that there will be a lot of political killings, assassinations, a lot of violence in America.
它只是意味着美国会出现大量政治杀人、暗杀，很多暴力。
Okay? Based on religious, political differences.
好吧？基于宗教、政治差异。
All right? So that's the second lesson to learn.
好的？这就是第二课。
From Rome. Aggression and
来自罗马。攻击与
violence will allow you to defeat your enemies.
暴力能让你击败敌人。
Once you do, this violence and aggression will turn inwards.
一旦这样，暴力与侵略就会向内转化。
Okay? And
好吧？而且
the third lesson that
第三课是
we can learn from Rome is, again, no societies are stable.
我们可以从罗马学到的又一件事是：没有任何社会是稳定的。
Everything changes over time.
一切都会随时间而变化。
So even though Rome was the dominant society,
于是即便罗马是主导社会，
the superpower of its time, it still collapsed.
其时代的超级大国，仍然崩溃。
And the same is true for America today.
同样的事今天的美国也一样。
So the world will change.
于是世界会变迁。
And it always changes. Okay?
而且它总是变化的。好吗？
So next class,
于是下节课，
we will look at the Roman Empire,
我们将来看看罗马帝国。
which is basically the Byzantine Empire.
它基本上就是拜占庭帝国。
Okay? Any questions about today's class?
好吗？今天的课有啥问题吗？
Are you guys clear? Okay.
你们明白了吗？好了。
Great. So I will see you next class.
好的。下节课再见。